<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Uncategorized | Tina Lasisi</title>
    <link>/category/uncategorized/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/uncategorized/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Uncategorized</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Tina Lasisi 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 13:07:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Uncategorized</title>
      <link>/category/uncategorized/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;So, where are the genes?&#34;- a brief intro to genetics for those who have no idea what&#39;s going on
</title>
      <link>/p225/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 13:07:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p225/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Overview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not too long ago, I had zero knowledge of genetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What this has to do with hair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genes – where are they? And some other basic stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analogies for how your DNA works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Links if you want to learn more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I didn’t know the first thing about genetics until I went to university&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my first year as an undergraduate, the Bio Anth classes I took were my first real exposure to genetics. In high school, I didn’t take any biology classes because I wanted to focus on languages and history (exactly &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I was not allowed to combine that with biology, as I wanted to do, is a story for another time). This lack of education on genetics meant that I was intensely terrified at the prospect of having to write essays on this topic during my first year. I remember my attempt to enlist the help of some first year bio-students to explain genetics to me. I remember clearly that my first question was something along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Okay, so, uhm, where exactly are &amp;#8220;the genes&amp;#8221;? &amp;#8211; &lt;/em&gt;a very confused Tina, circa 2011
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am currently by no stretch of the imagination a geneticist, I have since taken (and passed) quite a few exams on this topic and feel competent enough to explore the genetic literature on hair (and other topics). At times, I even feel bold enough to propose new research projects to my advisors! (I know, the audacity, right?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-259&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/06/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;giphy&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This long story is all just to say that it very much is possible to learn about genetics even if you are truly starting from scratch as an adult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now onto the meat of this post…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why are we even talking about genetics? This is a blog about hair evolution, right?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to understand how human hair diversity evolved. To do that I need to consider two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does hair vary in modern humans?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did this variation change over time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A genetic perspective can help answer both of those questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration:underline;&#34;&gt;Usefulness of a genetic approach to “How does hair vary in modern humans?&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why I need genetics
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appearance of hair texture + color is determined by both external and internal factors
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;external: hair products, straightening, coloring
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hold all external factors constant, and there is still variation among humans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;internal:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nutrition (kwashiokor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;age (balding, but also changing color/texture)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even when you hold all of *these* factors constant, there is still variation that appears to be inherent (to some degree), inheritable, and immutable
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;genetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration:underline;&#34;&gt;Usefulness of a genetic approach to “How did this variation change over time?&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human history goes further back than written records.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, unfortunately, in the case of hair and other “soft tissue”, no remains to look at (except in few mummy cases)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can find out when things appeared&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When things became more common in a population (signs of selection)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basics of genetics: where to find genetic stuff and what its called&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vocabulary
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DNA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;molecule vs atom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;basepairs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SNPs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;codons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your DNA is like…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lego/building blocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a bunch of code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analogies have their limitations of course, if an analogy were completely accurate, it would stop being an analogy and start being a description! But definitely handy stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get you some more knowledge!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crash course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
