<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>genetics | Tina Lasisi</title>
    <link>/tag/genetics/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/genetics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>genetics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Tina Lasisi 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>genetics</title>
      <link>/tag/genetics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shades of complexity: New perspectives on the evolution and genetic architecture of human skin</title>
      <link>/publication/quillen-ajpa-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/quillen-ajpa-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A non-expert&#39;s guide to the hype: Why is the Denisovan-Neanderthal &#34;hybrid&#34; such a big deal?
</title>
      <link>/2018/08/31/denisovan-neanderthal-hybrid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 10:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2018/08/31/denisovan-neanderthal-hybrid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#999999;&#34;&gt;Estimated reading time: 9 mins (1906 words)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you may have heard that a paper was recently published on the genome of a girl who lived around 90,000 years ago and was half-Neanderthal and half-Denisovan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, MY MOM WAS A NEANDERTHAL AND MY DAD WAS A DENISOVAN &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/rBsuFBQEBJ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/rBsuFBQEBJ&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Carl Zimmer (@carlzimmer) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/carlzimmer/status/1032345952189906945?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 22, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It kinda made the news…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people were excited, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; just geneticists and researchers working with human fossils. And my favorite thing about a science story going viral is that it brings out the comedy gold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    I&#39;m picturing a 13 year old starting secondary school and telling her new friends: &#34;me mam&#39;s a neanderthal, dad&#39;s a denisovan, bit of a nasty shock for him when he found out.&#34; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/I4fGRZEmO2&#34;&gt;https://t.co/I4fGRZEmO2&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Aoife Hardesty (@aoife_hardesty) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aoife_hardesty/status/1034131584964849664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    Do me like you&#39;re a neanderthal woman and I&#39;m a denisovan man.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Bʀɪᴀɴɪᴀᴄ® (@BGH70) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BGH70/status/1033064866096074753?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, even &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-06004-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Nature’s story on this publication&lt;/a&gt; was feeling cheeky:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-2408&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/nature_article.png&#34; alt=&#34;nature_article&#34; width=&#34;506&#34; height=&#34;757&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the ultimate tweets were without a doubt the Monty Python references:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    This is actually fascinating stuff, but I can&#39;t read &#34;Her mother was a Neanderthal, and her father was a Denisovan&#34; without hearing John Cleese&#39;s French taunter from Monty Python and the Holy Grail. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/AfthERMhSD&#34;&gt;https://t.co/AfthERMhSD&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Jon Hancock (@BigJackBrass) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BigJackBrass/status/1032570901047504896?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 23, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    The Neanderthal-Denisovan ancient mashup makes me think of this. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iGTqFFCCWZ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/iGTqFFCCWZ&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Sarah Parcak (@indyfromspace) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/indyfromspace/status/1032348084091736064?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 22, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while the news articles that ran on this story gave a good overview of why researchers were excited about it, without the historical context of how we’ve understood human evolution until now, it can be really hard to understand just how incredible this discovery is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s back up a little bit…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take you back all the way to when I was a wee baby undergrad…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_2409&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-2409&#34; style=&#34;width: 480px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-2409&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;giphy&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-2409&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Are you ready for story time, kids?&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2011 – an entire 7 years ago – I was just starting my first year at university. Going to all these lectures and learning about archaeology, social anthropology, and biological anthropology was really exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the thing I loved most, was all the time we got to have with the professors in small group settings. To this day, I truly believe that this aspect of Cambridge education is why I feel so comfortable in academia, but that’s a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the professors I spent the most time with, was the Archaeology professor at my college, Sir Paul Mellars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_2419&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-2419&#34; style=&#34;width: 628px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-2419&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/mellars.png&#34; alt=&#34;mellars.PNG&#34; width=&#34;628&#34; height=&#34;942&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-2419&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gettyimages.com/photos/sir-paul-mellars?alloweduse=availableforalluses&amp;family=creative&amp;license=rf&amp;phrase=sir%20paul%20mellars&amp;sort=best#license&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;This is a picture of him getting knighted by Prince Charles.&lt;/a&gt; I don&amp;#8217;t know why I find it so funny, but I can&amp;#8217;t help but laugh that I knew someone who went through such a fancy ritual.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember being terrified to meet him when I came to interview at Cambridge, but once I was actually in and after I’d had a few supervisions with him, that went away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_2410&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-2410&#34; style=&#34;width: 1164px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-2410&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/paul-mellars.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul Mellars&#34; width=&#34;1164&#34; height=&#34;873&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-2410&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;I know y&amp;#8217;all be like &amp;#8220;pics or it didn&amp;#8217;t happen&amp;#8221;, so hereby, pics of me, Paul Mellars and the other lovely anthropology students at Corpus Christi College.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Mellars is probably one of the most entertaining people I’ve ever met. Mostly because, in my eyes, he’s this fancy unicorn who is everything you’d imagine a Cambridge &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_don&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;don&lt;/a&gt; to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Mellars has this low booming voice, and he would often be smoking his pipe or a cigar in his office. Part of me kind of imagines that this is what Santa looks like in his time off,  which is something I obviously never mentioned to his face (and since I don’t expect he’s online much, I don’t think he’ll ever find out).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to get to the point, in our supervisions, he would always tell stories. It was one of my favorite things about him because, unlike other supervisors, he wouldn’t necessarily grill us with questions and I could rely on him doing most of the talking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I distinctly remember talking with him about was Neandertals and why they had gone “extinct”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Mellars wasn’t just any random archaeologist, after all. What he was known and knighted for was, in part, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16xwbv4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;his work on Neanderthals&lt;/a&gt;. He was an expert on stone tools of the Middle-Upper Paleolithic (~300,000-10,000 years ago).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By studying various stone tool &lt;em&gt;industries&lt;/em&gt; across Europe, archaeologists are able to say something about who might have been making them and when certain people came into contact with others or were perhaps replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_2411&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-2411&#34; style=&#34;width: 1280px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-2411&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/1280px-mousterian_points_and_scrapers_wellcome_m0015182.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;1280px-mousterian_points_and_scrapers_wellcome_m0015182&#34; width=&#34;1280&#34; height=&#34;920&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-2411&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;What we can learn from stone tools is awesome, but god I hated all my stone tool lectures and reading because looking at variously carved rocks for hours is something I simply don&amp;#8217;t have the attention span for.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So based on the fossil evidence, the archaeological/stone tool evidence, and the genetic evidence (at the time), it appeared that Neanderthals had simply vanished at some point. Or in any case, at some point, the skeletal morphology and stone tools we associate with Neanderthals was gone, and that time seemed to coincide with what was interpreted as the arrival of “anatomically modern humans”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of debate, but very few people who studied human evolution believed that Neanderthals had contributed to the modern human gene pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2012, during my second year, I remember writing essays about why Neanderthals might have disappeared, and evaluating the evidence about them having gone extinct vs having interbred with us. I remember asking Professor Mellars what he thought, and he said it was unlikely Neanderthals interbred with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of what I read about the disappearance of Neanderthals was that “modern humans” must have &lt;em&gt;outcompeted&lt;/em&gt; Neanderthals with our superior cognitive skills or &lt;em&gt;replaced&lt;/em&gt; them after they disappeared due to their inability to adapt to the changing climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t put my finger on it at the time, but I felt weird about the language that was being used around Neanderthals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also felt really uncomfortable that all explanations about this apparent disappearance of Neanderthals seemed to be centered on a post-hoc explanation of why “we” were simply better than them. Despite being wrapped in the language of natural selection, it seemed oddly &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00313220500106170&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;similar to 19th-century arguments naturalizing colonialism and the “inevitable demise” of certain peoples&lt;/a&gt;. And I am certainly not the first person to draw the link between natural selection, eugenics, and colonialism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But over the last few years, a lot of things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;theories-on-how-humans-evolved-one-origin-or-multiple&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theories on how humans evolved: one origin or multiple?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before genetic evidence really came onto the scene, most of what we had to base our understanding of human evolution on was fossil evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at this fossil evidence, during the late 20th century, two camps had formed: multiregionalists and those who thought modern humans were the product of a single-out-of-Africa expansion (clearly, the latter had a much less catchy group name, but I digress…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiregionalists saw continuity between the skeletal anatomy of archaic hominins (i.e. Neanderthals in Europe and &lt;em&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/em&gt; in Asia) and the respective modern populations in each continent. For example, some researchers emphasized the similarity between the “shovel-shaped” teeth found in &lt;em&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/em&gt;, and the presence of similar dental morphology in modern East Asian populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, proponents of the single ‘Out of Africa’ hypothesis saw similarities between the skeletal morphology of late African &lt;em&gt;Homo&lt;/em&gt; specimens and all modern humans. Some even went as far as to claim that all modern humans were the result of a ‘cognitive behavioral revolution’ around 70,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980’s, when researchers were finally able to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA_sequencing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;sequence&lt;/a&gt; mtDNA (DNA that is inherited maternally), it appeared to support the idea that all humans today traced their ancestry back, exclusively, to a single group based in Africa around 200,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, most people abandoned the multiregional hypothesis of human origins, but also any idea that Neanderthals (or other hominins) might have contributed to the modern gene pool at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-new-kid-on-the-block-ancient-dna&#34;&gt;The new kid on the block: Ancient DNA&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading about the history of science is fascinating because it shows the extent to which our knowledge is shaped by the technology we have, but also the questions we choose to ask and the tools we use to answer those questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re at all interested in understanding how weird and winding this path to our current understanding of Neanderthal/Denisovan/ancient human genetics was, I’d recommend you read Svante Pääbo’s autobiography ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/20/books/review/neanderthal-man-by-svante-paabo.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Neanderthal Man&lt;/a&gt;‘ where he discusses how he developed the methods that allowed researchers to extract and sequence ancient DNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to get back to our story, when we began analyzing ancient DNA, it was a pain and it was difficult. Getting even a small sequence was a huge victory. So when they got a bit of Neanderthal mtDNA sequenced in the late 1990’s, it was something worth celebrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When complete Neanderthal mtDNA sequences followed in 2008 and 2009, while exciting, the evidence still was in line with a single out of Africa expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, everything changed in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-2412&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/3880765.gif&#34; alt=&#34;3880765&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What many researchers in human evolution thought was true fundamentally changed when Svante Pääbo’s group published &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/328/5979/710&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;the draft sequence of the Neanderthal genome&lt;/a&gt; and concluded that &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/328/5979/680&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;there was evidence of Neanderthal introgression&lt;/a&gt; (genetic contribution) to modern day populations outside of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same year, their group also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature08976&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;published the mitochondrial (mtDNA) sequence of an unknown hominin&lt;/a&gt;, that appeared to group neither with modern humans nor with Neanderthals – &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/464838a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;we now refer to them as Denisovans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we were able to sequence the nuclear genomes of both Neanderthals and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature09710&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Denisovans&lt;/a&gt;, we were able to get the full picture, rather than just the matrilineal side of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there was an “ancient DNA rush” during this time, not everyone was convinced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, people were proposing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3435202/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;alternative hypotheses based on ancient population structure &lt;/a&gt;that could explain the genetic similarity we see between non-Africans and Neanderthals. In other words, what we see could be explained by the fact that non-Africans came from an ancestral population that was genetically more similar to Neanderthals, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/doubts-about-whether-modern-humans-and-neanderthals-interbred&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;but they did not interbreed with them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, we have commercially available genetic reports like 23andMe that will tell you just how Neanderthal you are. It’s unbelievable to think that only 5-6 years ago, many researchers would have thought that was plain wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_2413&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-2413&#34; style=&#34;width: 983px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-2413&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/neanderthal23andm3.png&#34; alt=&#34;neanderthal23andm3&#34; width=&#34;983&#34; height=&#34;370&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-2413&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Unfortunately, I&amp;#8217;m pretty low in Neanderthal since I&amp;#8217;m 50% African, but I&amp;#8217;m excited to get my mom&amp;#8217;s results!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-is-human-and-who-is-not&#34;&gt;Who is human and who is not?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the funny things I recall from undergrad is being told that I shouldn’t refer to Neanderthals as “humans” – that was reserved for “modern humans”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you think about it, that’s what this discussion is all about. From the beginning of anthropology, and even taxonomy, one of the key questions has been “who is human and who is not?” Is that line drawn between white Europeans and everyone else? Is that line drawn between Eurasians and Africans? Or is it drawn at some point in time, between those whose descendants are present today and those who have left no trace of their existence in populations today? And who gets to decide?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most difficult questions in human evolution: what does it mean to be human?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question is the reason why we have such awkward terminology as “modern humans” and “anatomically modern humans” and “behaviorally/cognitively modern humans” – they are all just clumsy attempts to essentialize the differences between groups of closely related people. But you can’t essentialize “humanness” because evolution doesn’t lend itself to clear divisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people still believe in the biological species concept. Meaning that we can define a species as a group of individuals that can bear fertile offspring. But most biologists know this definition is very limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    That the Biological Species Concept is the product of an attempt to rationalize an obsession with sorting messy reality into museum drawers. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/NclGXbtE7p&#34;&gt;https://t.co/NclGXbtE7p&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Magnus Nordborg (@magnusnordborg) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/magnusnordborg/status/1015523873322913792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The limitations of species concepts is also why we struggle to talk about this latest discovery – is this truly a hybrid? Is she just an admixed person between two different populations of the same species?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    &#34;&#39;We shy away a little from the word ‘hybrid’,&#39; says Pääbo. The term implies that the two groups are discrete species of human, whereas in reality the boundaries between them are blurry&#34; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ETCoqqREsV&#34;&gt;https://t.co/ETCoqqREsV&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; John Hawks (@johnhawks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/johnhawks/status/1032617342033899520?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 23, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    Infographic tracing the relationship between humans and ancient related species after scientists find evidence of a prehistoric love child between a Neanderthal and Denisovan&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hxmT8aPCBA&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hxmT8aPCBA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/YmaeiCVtQ8&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/YmaeiCVtQ8&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; AFP news agency (@AFP) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AFP/status/1032546386074583040?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 23, 2018&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth of the matter is that, at the moment, we don’t know, and that’s very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re learning about just how messy our history is, and how these neat boundaries we have been trying to draw around groups are making us miss the reality of the complex interactions between people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thinking back on just how much has changed over the last decade, I’m looking forward to the next decade to come – bring on the discoveries!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A non-expert&#39;s guide to the hype: Why is the Denisovan-Neanderthal &#34;hybrid&#34; such a big deal?</title>
      <link>/post/a-non-expert-s-guide-to-the-hype-why-is-the-denisovan-neanderthal-hybrid-such-a-big-deal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/a-non-expert-s-guide-to-the-hype-why-is-the-denisovan-neanderthal-hybrid-such-a-big-deal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, you may have heard that a paper was recently published on the genome of a girl who lived around 90,000 years ago and was half-Neanderthal and half-Denisovan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, Cohen, MY MOM WAS A NEANDERTHAL AND MY DAD WAS A DENISOVAN &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/rBsuFBQEBJ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/rBsuFBQEBJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Carl Zimmer (@carlzimmer) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/carlzimmer/status/1032345952189906945?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 22, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It kinda made the news…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people were excited, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just geneticists and researchers working with human fossils. And my favorite thing about a science story going viral is that it brings out the comedy gold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I&amp;#39;m picturing a 13 year old starting secondary school and telling her new friends: &amp;quot;me mam&amp;#39;s a neanderthal, dad&amp;#39;s a denisovan, bit of a nasty shock for him when he found out.&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/I4fGRZEmO2&#34;&gt;https://t.co/I4fGRZEmO2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Aoife Hardesty (@aoife_hardesty) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aoife_hardesty/status/1034131584964849664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Do me like you&amp;#39;re a neanderthal woman and I&amp;#39;m a denisovan man.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Bʀɪᴀɴɪᴀᴄ® (@BGH70) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BGH70/status/1033064866096074753?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, even 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-06004-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nature’s story on this publication&lt;/a&gt; was feeling cheeky:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/nature_denisovan_article.png&#34; alt=&#34;Nature&amp;rsquo;s Denisovan-Neanderthal story&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the ultimate tweets were without a doubt the Monty Python references:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This is actually fascinating stuff, but I can&amp;#39;t read &amp;quot;Her mother was a Neanderthal, and her father was a Denisovan&amp;quot; without hearing John Cleese&amp;#39;s French taunter from Monty Python and the Holy Grail. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/AfthERMhSD&#34;&gt;https://t.co/AfthERMhSD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jon Hancock (@BigJackBrass) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BigJackBrass/status/1032570901047504896?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 23, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The Neanderthal-Denisovan ancient mashup makes me think of this. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iGTqFFCCWZ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/iGTqFFCCWZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Scary Parcak 👻🎃 (@indyfromspace) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/indyfromspace/status/1032348084091736064?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 22, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while the news articles that ran on this story gave a good overview of why researchers were excited about it, without the historical context of how we’ve understood human evolution until now, it can be really hard to understand just how incredible this discovery is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s back up a little bit… I’d like to take you back all the way to when I was a wee baby undergrad…&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-are-you-ready-for-story-time-kids&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/story_time.gif&#34; data-caption=&#34;Are you ready for story time, kids?&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/story_time.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Are you ready for story time, kids?
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2011 – an entire 7 years ago – I was just starting my first year at university. Going to all these lectures and learning about archaeology, social anthropology, and biological anthropology was really exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the thing I loved most, was all the time we got to have with the professors in small group settings. To this day, I truly believe that this aspect of Cambridge education is why I feel so comfortable in academia, but that’s a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the professors I spent the most time with, was the Archaeology professor at my college, Sir Paul Mellars.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-this-is-a-picture-of-him-getting-knighted-by-prince-charles-i-dont-know-why-i-find-it-so-funny-but-i-cant-help-but-laugh-that-i-knew-someone-who-went-through-such-a-fancy-ritual&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/mellars_knighted.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;This is a picture of him getting knighted by Prince Charles. I don’t know why I find it so funny, but I can’t help but laugh that I knew someone who went through such a fancy ritual.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/mellars_knighted.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    This is a picture of him getting knighted by Prince Charles. I don’t know why I find it so funny, but I can’t help but laugh that I knew someone who went through such a fancy ritual.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember being terrified to meet him when I came to interview at Cambridge, but once I was actually in and after I’d had a few supervisions with him, that went away.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-i-know-yall-be-like-pics-or-it-didnt-happen-so-hereby-pics-of-me-paul-mellars-and-the-other-lovely-anthropology-students-at-corpus-christi-college&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/paul-mellars.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;I know y’all be like “pics or it didn’t happen”, so hereby, pics of me, Paul Mellars and the other lovely anthropology students at Corpus Christi College.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/paul-mellars.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    I know y’all be like “pics or it didn’t happen”, so hereby, pics of me, Paul Mellars and the other lovely anthropology students at Corpus Christi College.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Mellars is probably one of the most entertaining people I’ve ever met. Mostly because, in my eyes, he’s this fancy unicorn who is everything you’d imagine a Cambridge 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_%28honorific%29#Academia&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;don&lt;/a&gt; to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Mellars has this low booming voice, and he would often be smoking his pipe or a cigar in his office. Part of me kind of imagines that this is what Santa looks like in his time off,  which is something I obviously never mentioned to his face (and since I don’t expect he’s online much, I don’t think he’ll ever find out).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to get to the point, in our supervisions, he would always tell stories. It was one of my favorite things about him because, unlike other supervisors, he wouldn’t necessarily grill us with questions and I could rely on him doing most of the talking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I distinctly remember talking with him about was Neandertals and why they had gone “extinct”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Mellars wasn’t just any random archaeologist, after all. What he was known and knighted for was, in part, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16xwbv4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;his work on Neanderthals&lt;/a&gt;. He was an expert on stone tools of the Middle-Upper Paleolithic (~300,000-10,000 years ago).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By studying various stone tool &lt;em&gt;industries&lt;/em&gt; across Europe, archaeologists are able to say something about who might have been making them and when certain people came into contact with others or were perhaps replaced.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-what-we-can-learn-from-stone-tools-is-awesome-but-god-i-hated-all-my-stone-tool-lectures-and-reading-because-looking-at-variously-carved-rocks-for-hours-is-something-i-simply-dont-have-the-attention-span-for&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/stone_tools.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;What we can learn from stone tools is awesome, but god I hated all my stone tool lectures and reading because looking at variously carved rocks for hours is something I simply don’t have the attention span for.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/stone_tools.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    What we can learn from stone tools is awesome, but god I hated all my stone tool lectures and reading because looking at variously carved rocks for hours is something I simply don’t have the attention span for.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So based on the fossil evidence, the archaeological/stone tool evidence, and the genetic evidence (at the time), it appeared that Neanderthals had simply vanished at some point. Or in any case, at some point, the skeletal morphology and stone tools we associate with Neanderthals was gone, and that time seemed to coincide with what was interpreted as the arrival of “anatomically modern humans”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of debate, but very few people who studied human evolution believed that Neanderthals had contributed to the modern human gene pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2012, during my second year, I remember writing essays about why Neanderthals might have disappeared, and evaluating the evidence about them having gone extinct vs having interbred with us. I remember asking Professor Mellars what he thought, and he said it was unlikely Neanderthals interbred with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of what I read about the disappearance of Neanderthals was that “modern humans” must have &lt;em&gt;outcompeted&lt;/em&gt; Neanderthals with our superior cognitive skills or &lt;em&gt;replaced&lt;/em&gt; them after they disappeared due to their inability to adapt to the changing climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t put my finger on it at the time, but I felt weird about the language that was being used around Neanderthals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also felt really uncomfortable that all explanations about this apparent disappearance of Neanderthals seemed to be centered on a post-hoc explanation of why “we” were simply better than them. Despite being wrapped in the language of natural selection, it seemed oddly 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00313220500106170&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;similar to 19th-century arguments naturalizing colonialism and the “inevitable demise” of certain peoples&lt;/a&gt;. And I am certainly not the first person to draw the link between natural selection, eugenics, and colonialism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But over the last few years, a lot of things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;theories-on-how-humans-evolved-one-origin-or-multiple&#34;&gt;Theories on how humans evolved: one origin or multiple?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before genetic evidence really came onto the scene, most of what we had to base our understanding of human evolution on was fossil evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at this fossil evidence, during the late 20th century, two camps had formed: multiregionalists and those who thought modern humans were the product of a single-out-of-Africa expansion (clearly, the latter had a much less catchy group name, but I digress…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiregionalists saw continuity between the skeletal anatomy of archaic hominins (i.e. Neanderthals in Europe and &lt;em&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/em&gt; in Asia) and the respective modern populations in each continent. For example, some researchers emphasized the similarity between the “shovel-shaped” teeth found in &lt;em&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/em&gt;, and the presence of similar dental morphology in modern East Asian populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, proponents of the single ‘Out of Africa’ hypothesis saw similarities between the skeletal morphology of late African &lt;em&gt;Homo&lt;/em&gt; specimens and all modern humans. Some even went as far as to claim that all modern humans were the result of a ‘cognitive behavioral revolution’ around 70,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980’s, when researchers were finally able to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA_sequencing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sequence&lt;/a&gt; mtDNA (DNA that is inherited maternally), it appeared to support the idea that all humans today traced their ancestry back, exclusively, to a single group based in Africa around 200,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, most people abandoned the multiregional hypothesis of human origins, but also any idea that Neanderthals (or other hominins) might have contributed to the modern gene pool at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-new-kid-on-the-block-ancient-dna&#34;&gt;The new kid on the block: Ancient DNA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading about the history of science is fascinating because it shows the extent to which our knowledge is shaped by the technology we have, but also the questions we choose to ask and the tools we use to answer those questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re at all interested in understanding how weird and winding this path to our current understanding of Neanderthal/Denisovan/ancient human genetics was, I’d recommend you read Svante Pääbo’s autobiography 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/20/books/review/neanderthal-man-by-svante-paabo.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;‘Neanderthal Man‘&lt;/a&gt; where he discusses how he developed the methods that allowed researchers to extract and sequence ancient DNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to get back to our story, when we began analyzing ancient DNA, it was a pain and it was difficult. Getting even a small sequence was a huge victory. So when they got a bit of Neanderthal mtDNA sequenced in the late 1990’s, it was something worth celebrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When complete Neanderthal mtDNA sequences followed in 2008 and 2009, while exciting, the evidence still was in line with a single out of Africa expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, everything changed in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/fire_nation.gif&#34; alt=&#34;the fire nation attacks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What many researchers in human evolution thought was true fundamentally changed when Svante Pääbo’s group published the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/328/5979/710&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;draft sequence of the Neanderthal genome&lt;/a&gt; and concluded that there was 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/328/5979/680&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;evidence of Neanderthal introgression&lt;/a&gt; (genetic contribution) to modern day populations outside of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same year, their group also published the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature08976&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mitochondrial (mtDNA) sequence of an unknown hominin&lt;/a&gt;, that appeared to group neither with modern humans nor with Neanderthals – 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/464838a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;we now refer to them as Denisovans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we were able to sequence the nuclear genomes of both Neanderthals and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature09710&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Denisovans&lt;/a&gt;, we were able to get the full picture, rather than just the matrilineal side of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there was an “ancient DNA rush” during this time, not everyone was convinced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, people were proposing 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3435202/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;alternative hypotheses based on ancient population structure&lt;/a&gt; that could explain the genetic similarity we see between non-Africans and Neanderthals. In other words, what we see could be explained by the fact that non-Africans came from an ancestral population that was genetically more similar to Neanderthals, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/doubts-about-whether-modern-humans-and-neanderthals-interbred&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;but they did not interbreed with them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, we have commercially available genetic reports like 23andMe that will tell you just how Neanderthal you are. It’s unbelievable to think that only 5-6 years ago, many researchers would have thought that was plain wrong.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-unfortunately-im-pretty-low-in-neanderthal-since-im-50-african-but-im-excited-to-get-my-moms-results&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/23_and_me.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Unfortunately, I’m pretty low in Neanderthal since I’m 50% African, but I’m excited to get my mom’s results!&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/23_and_me.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Unfortunately, I’m pretty low in Neanderthal since I’m 50% African, but I’m excited to get my mom’s results!
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-human-and-who-is-not&#34;&gt;Who is human and who is not?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the funny things I recall from undergrad is being told that I shouldn’t refer to Neanderthals as “humans” – that was reserved for “modern humans”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you think about it, that’s what this discussion is all about. From the beginning of anthropology, and even taxonomy, one of the key questions has been “who is human and who is not?” Is that line drawn between white Europeans and everyone else? Is that line drawn between Eurasians and Africans? Or is it drawn at some point in time, between those whose descendants are present today and those who have left no trace of their existence in populations today? And who gets to decide?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most difficult questions in human evolution: what does it mean to be human?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question is the reason why we have such awkward terminology as “modern humans” and “anatomically modern humans” and “behaviorally/cognitively modern humans” – they are all just clumsy attempts to essentialize the differences between groups of closely related people. But you can’t essentialize “humanness” because evolution doesn’t lend itself to clear divisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people still believe in the biological species concept. Meaning that we can define a species as a group of individuals that can bear fertile offspring. But most biologists know this definition is very limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;That the Biological Species Concept is the product of an attempt to rationalize an obsession with sorting messy reality into museum drawers. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/NclGXbtE7p&#34;&gt;https://t.co/NclGXbtE7p&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Magnus Nordborg (@magnusnordborg) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/magnusnordborg/status/1015523873322913792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limitations of species concepts is also why we struggle to talk about this latest discovery – is this truly a hybrid? Is she just an admixed person between two different populations of the same species?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;#39;We shy away a little from the word ‘hybrid’,&amp;#39; says Pääbo. The term implies that the two groups are discrete species of human, whereas in reality the boundaries between them are blurry&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ETCoqqREsV&#34;&gt;https://t.co/ETCoqqREsV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; John Hawks (@johnhawks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/johnhawks/status/1032617342033899520?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 23, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Infographic tracing the relationship between humans and ancient related species after scientists find evidence of a prehistoric love child between a Neanderthal and Denisovan&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hxmT8aPCBA&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hxmT8aPCBA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/YmaeiCVtQ8&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/YmaeiCVtQ8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; AFP news agency (@AFP) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AFP/status/1032546386074583040?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 23, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth of the matter is that, at the moment, we don’t know, and that’s very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re learning about just how messy our history is, and how these neat boundaries we have been trying to draw around groups are making us miss the reality of the complex interactions between people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thinking back on just how much has changed over the last decade, I’m looking forward to the next decade to come – bring on the discoveries!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Next level science camp: teaching kids about their genetics &amp; genealogy</title>
      <link>/2017/11/04/next-level-science-camp-teaching-kids-about-their-genetics-genealogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 12:44:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2017/11/04/next-level-science-camp-teaching-kids-about-their-genetics-genealogy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#808080;&#34;&gt;Estimated reading time: 3 mins (610 words)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I&amp;#8217;ve watched enough American TV to know that summer camp is a thing in the USA.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I was introduced to it through the classic twin movies: It Takes Two and The Parent Trap.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1910&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1910&#34; style=&#34;width: 500px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1910&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;giphy&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;342&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1910&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;These movies have given me the false expectation that you always meet your twin at summer camp, though&amp;#8230;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  And the wondrous thing about American summer camps is that they don&amp;#8217;t just come in one flavor! There&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;band&lt;/em&gt; camp, &lt;em&gt;sports&lt;/em&gt; camp, &lt;em&gt;adventure&lt;/em&gt; camp, &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt; camp, &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; camp, anything-you-can-come-up-with-camp!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  And this summer, I got to see kids doing a very special type of science camp &amp;#8211; one that was about &lt;em&gt;genetics and genealogy&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;When science is personal, it&amp;#8217;s more relatable and understandable&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  To quote &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HenryLouisGates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Henry Louis Gates Jr&lt;/a&gt;.: &amp;#8220;Kids love to study &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;selves&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-1980 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/giphy3.gif&#34; alt=&#34;giphy3&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I&amp;#8217;m the kind of person who will take time out of their day to click on a headline that says: &amp;#8220;Answer these 7 questions and we&amp;#8217;ll tell you what flavor of donut your soul is&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  So, let&amp;#8217;s just say that I&amp;#8217;m a sucker for learning stuff about myself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  And, clearly, I&amp;#8217;m not alone! When my advisor, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sites.psu.edu/ninajablonski/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Nina Jablonski&lt;/a&gt;, was telling me about this camp, she explained that the idea behind the genetics &amp; genealogy camp was making science personally meaningful.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  When you are learning about yourself, you&amp;#8217;re invested and you&amp;#8217;re curious. And this summer, I saw that these young scientists were truly engaged with all of this material in an amazing way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Topics like DNA, evolution, and history were no longer a collection of abstract facts, but tools for these kids to answer questions they had about themselves.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I thought was really amazing about this particular camp was the combination of the genetics with the genealogy. Starting off by thinking about your grandparents and great-grandparents is a great way of showing that (human) &lt;em&gt;evolution is just an extension of history. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Here, they called us scientists” – Adalynn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I heard this, it made me so happy that I nearly cried. Yes, I’m an emotional person. But seriously though, I’m a 25-year old Ph.D. student and this year was probably the first time a professor had referred to me as a scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Letting these kids know they were scientists was so empowering! I honestly think that just by doing that, they’ve been immunized against &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/careers/2008/02/no-youre-not-impostor&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt; (grad students know what I’m talking about, sadly….).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_2022&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-2022&#34; style=&#34;width: 1014px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-2022 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/brandon-is-the-bomb.png&#34; alt=&#34;Brandon is the bomb&#34; width=&#34;1014&#34; height=&#34;518&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-2022&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;The camp&amp;#8217;s amazing instructor, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bigdata_kane&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Brandon Ogbunu&lt;/a&gt;, made sure these kids knew _they_ were in charge and could do anything they set their minds to&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching it all come together: &lt;em&gt;Finding Your Roots – The Seedlings &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  While I&amp;#8217;m still pretty salty that I couldn&amp;#8217;t be snuck in to participate as a slightly older, oversized child, watching the web series following this summer&amp;#8217;s camp is arguably the next best thing!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about the genetics and genealogy camp, watch the episodes – I promise you’ll love them (I’ve embedded the videos below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, there are three of these 8-minute gems, and the next 5 episodes will come out over the next few weeks. If you want to keep up with this series, bookmark &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fyrclassroom.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;fyrclassroom.org&lt;/a&gt; and check out the “episodes” tab, or keep an eye on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/weta/finding-your-roots/classroom/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;PBS website&lt;/a&gt;. You can also &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TinaLasisi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; because I will definitely be updating on each and every episode that is released!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good reason to bookmark the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fyrclassroom.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;FYR website&lt;/a&gt; is that you’ll find all of the teaching material for each episode as it comes out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perfect if you want to bring ‘Finding Your Roots’ to your classroom. (Or if you are like me and want to do this awesome &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fyrclassroom.org/episodes/episode-2-dna-extraction.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Fruit DNA Extraction&lt;/a&gt; thing yourself – why should kids have all the fun????)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with that, I’ll leave you to enjoy the episodes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&#34;Finding Your Roots: The Seedlings - Episode 1&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/j7CChvmfM_s?feature=oembed&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&#34;Finding Your Roots: The Seedlings - DNA Extraction (Episode 2)&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xdJUKr8dE-0?feature=oembed&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&#34;Finding Your Roots: The Seedlings - DNA Ancestry (Episode 3)&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2M7YqYBUHRM?feature=oembed&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[blog_subscription_form]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surprise! Africans are not all the same! (Or why we need diversity in science)</title>
      <link>/2017/10/18/surprise-africans-are-not-all-the-same-or-why-we-need-diversity-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 08:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2017/10/18/surprise-africans-are-not-all-the-same-or-why-we-need-diversity-in-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#808080;&#34;&gt;Estimated reading time: 12 mins (2250 words)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Edit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-018-1395-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Link to an article&lt;/a&gt; I wrote with my advisor about African skin pigmentation genetics in &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Last week, a research article was published on skin color variation &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; Africa.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1522&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1522&#34; style=&#34;width: 800px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1522&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/crawford-et-al.png&#34; alt=&#34;crawford et al&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;260&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1522&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Last week&amp;#8217;s article on African skin color in _Science_&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/early/2017/10/11/science.aan8433&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;READ IT!&lt;/a&gt; It is great, well-written, and has amazing figures! I would actually show you some of those figures if I wasn&amp;#8217;t terrified of publishers coming after me for copyright infringement (look, I&amp;#8217;m trying to finish a Ph.D., here, so I don&amp;#8217;t have time to get sued by journal publishers&amp;#8230;).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  If you don&amp;#8217;t have access to these journals, hit up your nearest scholar and ask them for a copy (you can email me!).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  And one of the things I really appreciate in this article is that it&amp;#8217;s a study on variation in Africa that actually includes &lt;em&gt;African authors&lt;/em&gt; from African institutions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;This research is important.&lt;/strong&gt; That&amp;#8217;s why it was picked up by The New York Times and The Atlantic. These articles are all full of people emphasizing that African diversity is an amazing thing that we need to pay attention to!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Read both of those articles too because they are full of quotes that got me feeling some type of way:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We knew quite a lot about why people have pale skin if they had European ancestry,” said Nicholas G. Crawford, a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Pennsylvania and a co-author of the new study. &lt;strong&gt;“But there was very little known about why people have dark skin.”&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/10/12/science/skin-color-race.html?mwrsm=Facebook&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few human traits are more variable, more obvious, and more historically divisive than the color of our skin. And yet, for all its social and scientific importance, we know very little about how our genes influence its pigment. **What we do know comes almost entirely from studying people of European descent. **– &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/10/a-brief-history-of-the-genes-that-color-our-skin/542694/?utm_source=twb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Ed Yong via The Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  And there you have it, in bold, the reason I ended up doing a Ph.D. in biological anthropology. I wanted to know more about human biological variation, and I specifically wanted to focus on African diversity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Why is so much of the research on human trait variation focused on Europeans?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember, as an undergraduate, hearing so many times that “Africans have the most genetic diversity” but when it came to looking at trait variation, especially skin color, hair color and hair form, all of a sudden, it was like Africans were just a monolith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I remember looking for articles on variation in African pigmentation and hair, but all I could find was dozens of articles on how Europeans had all of these &amp;#8216;diverse&amp;#8217; hair colors and hair types, but Africans could just be described as homogeneously &amp;#8220;dark&amp;#8221; and their hair was simply &amp;#8220;frizzy&amp;#8221;. Mind you, these are not articles from the 19th century, these are things that were published from 2000 onwards.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Research saying that &amp;#8220;Africans have the most genetic diversity&amp;#8221; started to sound a lot like paying lip service without actually believing it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Looking at the 23andMe genetic testing results, I don&amp;#8217;t get the impression that we really respect the idea that &amp;#8220;Africans have the most genetic diversity&amp;#8221; because these are the reference populations for ancestry in Europeans vs Africans:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&#34; size-full wp-image-1823 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/european-tested-populations-23andme.png&#34; alt=&#34;European tested populations 23andme&#34; width=&#34;390&#34; height=&#34;894&#34; /&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; size-full wp-image-1824 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/african-tested-populations-23andme.png&#34; alt=&#34;African tested populations 23andMe&#34; width=&#34;389&#34; height=&#34;308&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I mean, you can tell me if I&amp;#8217;ve got &amp;#8220;Balkan&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;French &amp; German&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Finnish&amp;#8221; ancestry but the categories for Africa span a third of the continent? That&amp;#8217;s a problem. But at least, 23andMe is aware of it&amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&#34; size-full wp-image-1828 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/23andme-ancestry-bias.png&#34; alt=&#34;23andMe ancestry bias&#34; width=&#34;767&#34; height=&#34;303&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Why does &amp;#8220;the public&amp;#8221; believe skin color = race?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Based on the titles of the news articles, you&amp;#8217;d think the problem is that everyone equates skin color with race.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1799&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1799&#34; style=&#34;width: 528px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1799&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/headline-for-nyt.png&#34; alt=&#34;Headline for NYT&#34; width=&#34;528&#34; height=&#34;96&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1799&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Headline from the New York Times&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1801&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1801&#34; style=&#34;width: 639px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1801&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/headline-for-quartz.png&#34; alt=&#34;Headline for Quartz&#34; width=&#34;639&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1801&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Headline from Quartz&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1802&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1802&#34; style=&#34;width: 561px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1802&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/headline-for-science-alert.png&#34; alt=&#34;Headline for Science Alert&#34; width=&#34;561&#34; height=&#34;110&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1802&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Headline from Science Alert&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1803&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1803&#34; style=&#34;width: 688px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1803&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/iflscience-headline.png&#34; alt=&#34;iflscience headline&#34; width=&#34;688&#34; height=&#34;135&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1803&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Headline from IFL Science&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  From these headlines, I guess the question should be: &amp;#8220;Who believes race = skin color?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Surely the Africans living in Africa and traveling around the continent would have noticed that there is a huge range of variation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Is this an American/European problem?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Maybe this does indeed have something to do with who, historically, has designed the racial categories.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  When Linnaeus first divided humans up into subspecies, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_racism#Carl_Linnaeus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;skin color was indeed one of the classifiers of the different &amp;#8216;human races&amp;#8217;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1835&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1835&#34; style=&#34;width: 436px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; size-full wp-image-1835 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/linnean-e1508271734129.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;linnean&#34; width=&#34;436&#34; height=&#34;277&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1835&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Linnaeus original classification of human &amp;#8216;variants&amp;#8217;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  But then again, despite decades of critiques, humans can still be categorized by racialized groups that use skin color as a classifier if we take a peek at the U.S. census categories:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1814&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1814&#34; style=&#34;width: 857px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; size-full wp-image-1814 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/us-census-categories.png&#34; alt=&#34;us census categories&#34; width=&#34;857&#34; height=&#34;163&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1814&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.census.gov/topics/population/race/about.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Currently on the U.S. census website&lt;/a&gt;. And, honestly, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pewsocialtrends.org/interactives/multiracial-timeline/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;looking at the history of the terms, it&amp;#8217;s been worse.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Yes, there is certainly a lag time between scientific consensus and public understanding.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  But the problem isn&amp;#8217;t just with &amp;#8220;the public&amp;#8221; understanding science, it&amp;#8217;s also a problem of the things that have been done in the name of science.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Scientific &amp;#8216;objectivity&amp;#8217; doesn&amp;#8217;t mean the field of human biology gets a pass on diversity.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Whenever I read about scientific racism, I inevitably come across some claim that the great thing about Science is that &amp;#8216;it&amp;#8217;s objective&amp;#8217; and that Science is self-correcting and will eventually uncover The Truth™.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  But the problem is the Science isn&amp;#8217;t some great force in the universe that just happens. Science is done by scientists, and &lt;em&gt;who those scientists are matters&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Some people genuinely believe that it doesn&amp;#8217;t matter &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; does science as long as it is done correctly The Truth™ will shine through. But that isn&amp;#8217;t necessarily true.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  No matter how perfect your application of the scientific method is (and, honestly, it rarely is applied perfectly), there is still room for bias.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Just because the process of science is supposed to be objective, doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that the hypotheses we think up come from a place of objectivity. Hypotheses are inspired by what we see in the world around us, and that is fundamentally influenced by our perspectives and experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  This bias in the hypotheses is especially obvious articles written about sexual selection in skin and hair color and almost everything you find will be about how &amp;#8216;white skin&amp;#8217; and &amp;#8216;blond hair&amp;#8217; evolved because these are attractive traits (with little to no evidence as to why that is so, just trust the author on this, obviously, this is a fact).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  This bias in hypotheses is undeniable in the fact that when we talk about the (pseudo)scientific work on &amp;#8216;racial&amp;#8217; differences in intelligence, it is always about the supposed superiority of &amp;#8216;white&amp;#8217; or &amp;#8216;European&amp;#8217; people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  There is a very straightforward relationship between those who, historically, have done the science, and who comes out on top when &amp;#8216;scientists&amp;#8217; ask questions about what traits are attractive or superior.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8220;Scientific racism is a thing of the past&amp;#8221; &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Just because the &amp;#8216;Annals of Eugenics&amp;#8217; has changed its name to the &amp;#8216;Annals of Human Genetics&amp;#8217; doesn&amp;#8217;t mean we&amp;#8217;ve undone centuries of scientific racism.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Just because there have been hundreds of articles and books on scientific racism doesn&amp;#8217;t mean we&amp;#8217;ve overcome the systematic and structural problems that made it necessary for those articles and books to be written.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Of course, there has been progress. Many scientists have called out racist work and, some, have even dedicated their lives to fighting scientific racism. For most of the biased hypotheses I mentioned above, there have been eloquent responses by other white researchers pointing out the flaws in those works and questioning the validity of hypotheses seeking to prove superiority.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  But why do we rely on white scientists to call out other white scientists? Why is science, especially the science of human biological variation, such a &amp;#8216;white space&amp;#8217;?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  A few years ago, James Watson clearly felt comfortable enough to say that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/fury-at-dna-pioneers-theory-africans-are-less-intelligent-than-westerners-394898.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;&amp;#8216;Africans are less intelligent&amp;#8217;&lt;/a&gt;. The fact that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/dec/01/dna-james-watson-scientist-selling-nobel-prize-medal&#34;&gt;he didn&amp;#8217;t expect the backlash&lt;/a&gt; should tell us something about the academic environment he had been living in until that point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  The biggest structural problem in science today is that, in the most &amp;#8216;prestigious&amp;#8217; societies, institutions and journals (those that have the most power to construct the scientific narrative), it remains overrepresented by certain demographic groups (i.e. white, male, English-speaking), and underrepresented by others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  This influences the kind of science that is done. And it most certainly influences the kind of bad science that slips through the cracks and the kind of biases that are shared behind closed doors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Diversity isn&amp;#8217;t just necessary for fighting &amp;#8216;scientific racism&amp;#8217;, it&amp;#8217;s necessary for improving the quality of science.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Even with the best of intentions, scientists can perpetuate stereotypes. In the case of skin color, clearly, there have been a lot of researchers who could not see any the large variation on the darker end of the skin pigmentation spectrum.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  This is what I like to refer to as the &amp;#8217;50 shades of Beige&amp;#8217; problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  This is the reason why Rihanna&amp;#8217;s Fenty Beauty line of foundation has done so well &amp;#8211; Rihanna recognizes the wide range of skin colors that exist, especially on the darker end of the spectrum.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_1690&#34; aria-describedby=&#34;caption-attachment-1690&#34; style=&#34;width: 1200px&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1690&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/fenty-foundation.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;fenty foundation&#34; width=&#34;1200&#34; height=&#34;1400&#34; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&#34;caption-attachment-1690&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Range of shades available for Rihanna&amp;#8217;s Fenty Beauty&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  This is a contrast with companies that manufacture products for all the shades of light skin that exist, but apparently, believe that dark-skinned people are one uniform shade:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&#34; size-full wp-image-1694 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/ysl-foundation.png&#34; alt=&#34;YSL foundation&#34; width=&#34;631&#34; height=&#34;879&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Luckily for scientific work on skin color, we have machines that can measure skin color objectively (reflectance spectrophotometers), so we&amp;#8217;ve been able to quantify the great range of diversity that there has been for a while now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  But despite the fact that there have been some researchers who&amp;#8217;ve pointed out this diversity for more than a decade, most of the research on skin color (and its genetics) has remained pretty focused on variation found in Western countries:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  The first gene identified as affecting human skin color—MC1R—is very diverse in European populations but remarkably similar across African ones. Based on that pattern, says Tishkoff, some geneticists have concluded that the evolutionary pressure for dark skin in Africa is so strong that any genetic variants that altered skin color were ruthlessly weeded out by natural selection. &lt;strong&gt;“That’s not true,” says Tishkoff—but it’s what happens when you only study skin color in Western countries. “When you look at this African-centered perspective, there’s a lot of variation.”&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/10/a-brief-history-of-the-genes-that-color-our-skin/542694/?utm_source=twb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  We need an African-centered perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  This is especially true in my area of study &amp;#8211; human hair diversity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Even with skin color, which we can measure objectively, there&amp;#8217;s been a bias in the research and homogenization of African variation, so just imagine for a second what the situation is like for hair variation, which we don&amp;#8217;t yet have good methods of measurement for.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I can tell you, the situation is pretty bad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  While people have suggested a number of ways of measuring hair curl, if you look for genetic studies of people&amp;#8217;s hair, what you&amp;#8217;ll find is that researchers simply categorize people&amp;#8217;s hair visually into: &amp;#8216;straight&amp;#8217;, &amp;#8216;wavy&amp;#8217; or &amp;#8216;curly&amp;#8217; &amp;#8211; and not so surprisingly, these studies focus on European hair variation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms10815&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;One of my favorite genetic studies&lt;/a&gt; on pigmentation and hair form uses a diverse group of Latin Americans, but guess what their categories are for hair curl? &amp;#8216;Straight&amp;#8217;, &amp;#8216;wavy&amp;#8217;, &amp;#8216;curly&amp;#8217; and &amp;#8216;frizzy&amp;#8217;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Like I said, even the best of intentions won&amp;#8217;t save you from the need for diversity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  The Afro-descendant people in that study cohort probably had a range of hair textures and to reduce that variation to &amp;#8216;frizzy&amp;#8217; is not just problematic because it&amp;#8217;s an insulting term, it also homogenizes a group of diverse people using the hair equivalent of the &amp;#8217;50 shades of Beige&amp;#8217; approach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I understand the need to use categories if you have a huge amount of data and no good way to measure a trait. But there are options.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  And if there had been African or Afro-descendant women involved with the design of the study, I&amp;#8217;d think someone would have pointed out that for a few years now, there have been more sophisticated categorizations people with tightly curled hair use to describe their hair types:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&#34; size-full wp-image-1726 aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/curly-hair-types.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;curly hair types&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;442&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Think of all the scientific discoveries we are missing out on because we don&amp;#8217;t seek the perspectives of people who can see all of this variation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Hopefully, in a few years, we can do with hair what we have done for skin and then we can happily read articles telling us about the huge range of diversity in hair within Africa.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Hopefully, in a few years, we won&amp;#8217;t be as &amp;#8216;surprised&amp;#8217; that Africans are not all the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Again, I&amp;#8217;m very excited about the article that just came out and I will continue to share the hell out of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-width=&#34;550&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
    “Africa is not some homogenous place where everyone has dark skin. There’s huge variation.” YES, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SarahTishkoff?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@SarahTishkoff&lt;/a&gt;, TELL THEM!!! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hsl3GciB0m&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hsl3GciB0m&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Tina Lasisi (@TinaLasisi) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TinaLasisi/status/918578476516630529?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 12, 2017&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I just wish we weren&amp;#8217;t so surprised about African diversity, and I believe this &amp;#8216;surprise&amp;#8217; is related to the fact that &lt;em&gt;even when Africans and Afro-descendants are the subjects of scientific interest, we are not often enough the ones shaping the work that is being done&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Diversity in other areas of science and other types of diversity&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  I&amp;#8217;ve kept this post centered on the biological anthropology/human biology aspect of science because that&amp;#8217;s the discipline I&amp;#8217;m familiar with. Of course, there are other areas in science that would benefit from diversity and there are excellent articles and posts about that from other people on e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/how-can-we-give-black-and-latino-astronomers-foundation-reach-stars-180960213/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;astronomy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/blogs/education/2015/05/mathematics-pipeline-uncommon-dialogue/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;mathematics&lt;/a&gt;. Some excellent people to follow on this issue include the astrophysicists &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/IBJIYONGI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Chanda Prescod-Weinstein&lt;/a&gt; &amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JedidahIslerPhD&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Jedidah Isler&lt;/a&gt;, the biologist &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DNLee5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Danielle Lee&lt;/a&gt; and the podcasts &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/VanguardSTEM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;VanguardSTEM&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&#34;gr-progress&#34; href=&#34;https://twitter.com/phdivaspodcast&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;PhDivas&lt;/a&gt;. And &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/voices/diversity-in-stem-what-it-is-and-why-it-matters/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;here&amp;#8217;s another article &lt;/a&gt;on diversity in STEM just to get you going.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  Most of what I&amp;#8217;ve talked about here is the way in which black/African opinions would impact science, but it is important to include other underrepresented perspectives as well. These include (but are not limited to) perspectives from: non-English speakers (there&amp;#8217;s a whole world out there that&amp;#8217;s ignored because people can&amp;#8217;t publish in what happened to become the &amp;#8220;common&amp;#8221; language), non-Western people, people from non-industrialized societies, people who&amp;#8217;ve grown up in poverty, LGBTQ people &amp;#8211; all of these need to have a voice in science if we truly want to strive for excellence and innovation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:justify;&#34;&gt;
  [blog_subscription_form]
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;So, where are the genes?&#34;- a brief intro to genetics for those who have no idea what&#39;s going on
</title>
      <link>/p225/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 13:07:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/p225/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Overview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not too long ago, I had zero knowledge of genetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What this has to do with hair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genes – where are they? And some other basic stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analogies for how your DNA works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Links if you want to learn more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I didn’t know the first thing about genetics until I went to university&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my first year as an undergraduate, the Bio Anth classes I took were my first real exposure to genetics. In high school, I didn’t take any biology classes because I wanted to focus on languages and history (exactly &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I was not allowed to combine that with biology, as I wanted to do, is a story for another time). This lack of education on genetics meant that I was intensely terrified at the prospect of having to write essays on this topic during my first year. I remember my attempt to enlist the help of some first year bio-students to explain genetics to me. I remember clearly that my first question was something along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Okay, so, uhm, where exactly are &amp;#8220;the genes&amp;#8221;? &amp;#8211; &lt;/em&gt;a very confused Tina, circa 2011
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am currently by no stretch of the imagination a geneticist, I have since taken (and passed) quite a few exams on this topic and feel competent enough to explore the genetic literature on hair (and other topics). At times, I even feel bold enough to propose new research projects to my advisors! (I know, the audacity, right?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-259&#34; src=&#34;https://humanhairdiversity.files.wordpress.com/2017/06/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;giphy&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This long story is all just to say that it very much is possible to learn about genetics even if you are truly starting from scratch as an adult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now onto the meat of this post…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why are we even talking about genetics? This is a blog about hair evolution, right?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to understand how human hair diversity evolved. To do that I need to consider two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does hair vary in modern humans?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did this variation change over time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A genetic perspective can help answer both of those questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration:underline;&#34;&gt;Usefulness of a genetic approach to “How does hair vary in modern humans?&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why I need genetics
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appearance of hair texture + color is determined by both external and internal factors
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;external: hair products, straightening, coloring
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hold all external factors constant, and there is still variation among humans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;internal:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nutrition (kwashiokor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;age (balding, but also changing color/texture)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even when you hold all of *these* factors constant, there is still variation that appears to be inherent (to some degree), inheritable, and immutable
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;genetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration:underline;&#34;&gt;Usefulness of a genetic approach to “How did this variation change over time?&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human history goes further back than written records.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, unfortunately, in the case of hair and other “soft tissue”, no remains to look at (except in few mummy cases)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can find out when things appeared&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When things became more common in a population (signs of selection)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basics of genetics: where to find genetic stuff and what its called&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vocabulary
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DNA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;molecule vs atom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;basepairs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SNPs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;codons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your DNA is like…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lego/building blocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a bunch of code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analogies have their limitations of course, if an analogy were completely accurate, it would stop being an analogy and start being a description! But definitely handy stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get you some more knowledge!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crash course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
